We're here with Daisy today, to talk about removing ear wax from a cat's ear.
Now there's various reasons that a cat will get ear wax.
Mites can be a big one.
Fungus can be another.
Mites, usually they look a little bit like coffee grounds that have accumulated in the cat's ear.
A, a fungus will have kind of a yeasty smell if you touch it and then put it to your nose.
In those cases you really want to take the cat to the vet and have the vet treat them for mites, or treat them for the fungus.
Some cats get a lot of waxy build up just because they're kind of a waxy cat.
Or perhaps they have food allergies or some other allergy.
So I've put a little bit of ear cleaner, cat ear cleaner on this little pad and we're just going to reach around in here, there's a lot of little crevices in the ear.
The outside of the ear you really want to get that because it can get some build up there.
These little crevices back here, oh yes, she's being such a good girl.
Daisy is an incredibly well behaved cat and I'm not even having to scruff her.
Which is great.
Alright, with a cat that's a little less cooperative, you see this loose, loose skin right here at the back of the neck.
You can just scruff that.
It's a great way to hold this cat secure, you can sort of press down a little bit, keep them flat against the, the sink, the towel is really nice, or against the counter.
The towel is nice to give them something to put their nails into something if it will make them feel secure.
And it keeps your counter clean.
And we're going to come over here and do the other side.
There you go sweety.
How's that?
Oh not a whole lot going on today.
Now for some cats the easiest thing to do is swaddle them in the towel.
I wouldn't do this with a cat that you don't know well.
But for one of your own cats it can help them feel more secure, and it can also keep them from using their little claws to, to try and fight anything you're doing that they don't like.
So you just want to get in here and clean around.
You really don't want to go any deeper than where your finger will reach because you don't want to damage their ear, their eardrum.
And a just nice gentle massaging motion.
Hopefully, it could actually, the thing that's amazing about cat grooming is it can actually be pleasurable for the cat if you take the right attitude.
Doesn't that feel good?
Doesn't that feel nice and clean?
Oh aren't you a good kitty Daisy?
Yeah, and look your ears are so pretty.